<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A compendyous treatyse of sclau[n]dre declarynge what sclaundre is, and what it sygnifyeth, and how many kyndes of sclaundre there be.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1545</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13917</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24216A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106198</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841919</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841919</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6539</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13917)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6539)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 582:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A compendyous treatyse of sclau[n]dre declarynge what sclaundre is, and what it sygnifyeth, and how many kyndes of sclaundre there be.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In the Old bayly in saynt Sepulchres parysshe, by me Rychard Lant,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1545?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Libel and slander --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6539:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6539:1"/>
            <p>A compen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyous treatyſe of ſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre / declarynge what ſclaundre is / and what it ſygnifyeth / and how many kyndes of ſclaundre there be.</p>
            <p>¶ Wo be vnto him by whom ſclaundre com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth. Mathew. xviii. Beware therfore what thou ſpekeſt / of whom and by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / that it be not for euyll wyl or ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyce / leſt thou be in dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gre of iudgement.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:6539:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6539:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Claundre is or ſynifieeh an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence / whereby mans mynd is ſore diſquietid or trobled: that is to ſay / it is other diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged or couraged to or fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the imitacyon or folowynge of a thing.<note place="margin">ii. maner of ſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dres. one phariſcy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>call / ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> leaf; There is a double kynde of ſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre / one is pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſaycall / which comenly they call ſclaundre taken: and that is whan that ypocrytes be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded other with right doctry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne / or with neceſſary doyng / &amp; therupon cometh hatred of the goſpell and of godly men: as the phariſyes hated the goſpel and the teachers of the ſame / &amp; pretended gret cauſes of their grefe &amp; hatered taken of mans<note place="margin">Mat. xv</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:6539:3"/>wytte &amp; reaſon: for what man endued but with a meane wyt wolde not be greued / that the facyon of relygion ſhulde any thing decay / that comen peace ſhuld be diſquyeted / that ſyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes ſhulde ryſe in the church / that hye powers and commen welthes ſhulde be brought to nought. They ſawe that their relygion &amp; maner of worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of god was lytle eſtemed and that the comen welth was hyndred / and the auctoritye of ſuperyoures contempned: But although theſe be great cauſes / which worthely doth moue men / yet it is mete to know / that before theſe cauſes yea / before all thynges / that the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of god be prefarred after this rule: It is
<pb facs="tcp:6539:3"/>neceſſary rather to obeye God than men.<note place="margin">Actu. v.</note> Therfore this pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſaycall ſclaunder or offence is not to be eſchewed / for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement of god excuſeth vs. But it is neceſſary y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne be true certayne &amp; profy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the church. For it is a very greuous ſyn to troble the church with euyll / vncertayne or vnprofytable diſputacions.</p>
            <p>leaf; There is another kynde of ſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre / which they call ſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre gyuen.<note place="margin">Sclaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> And it is vngodly doctryne or euyl exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple which hurteth / other bycauſe they fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowe it / or bycauſe it ſcarreth men from the goſpell. All wyc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked doctrynes ar ſclaundres &amp; offences of this kynde. Alſo i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrers worſhippynge and mens inuencyons / which can
<pb facs="tcp:6539:4"/>not be obſerued &amp; kept without ſynne: as worſhippyng of y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages / goyng on pylgryma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / purchaſyng of popyſſhe pardons for remiſſyon of ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Chriſt threat the auctors of theſe ſclaunders chefely.</p>
            <p>leaf; Wo be to the men by whom ſclaundre cometh.<note place="margin">Mathei. xviii.</note> &amp; ce. Than theſe ſclaundres and offences with great dilygence muſt be eſchewed / leſt we be other auc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tours or alowers of vngodly doctryne &amp; folowers of ſuche wycked worſhippyng. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A rule of the vſe of lyber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye.</note>leaf; There is alſo another kynd of ſclaundre to be eſchewed / that is / wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that a work which is indyfferent / is done out of tyme: as the vntymely vſe of chriſtyan lyberte. Of this ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berte / there is often dyſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyons
<pb facs="tcp:6539:4"/>and reaſonyng / whan it is lawfull / and whan it is not lawfull. It is ſynne to breake mens tradicyons / in caſe that the brekyng of them ſhulde be occaſyon of ſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre or offence to any man. Therfore the rule of Poule is to be holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as tou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chyng the vſe of lyberte.<note place="margin">Rom. xv</note> Poul co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth the lerned men to bere thinfyrmyte of the vnler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and weke / &amp; folowe their myndes / and certify them for their good &amp; for their edifyeng that is / that through their gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tylnes they may courage them to the Goſpell and not ſkarte them: For not alonly ipocryts and the vngodly ſorte / but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo godly men / &amp; men of ſobre lyuyng / ſpecyally they that be not taught nor ſuffyciently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructe
<pb facs="tcp:6539:5"/>whan they ſe auncyent cuſtomes broken / they iudge by that maner of doctryne / men to be gyuen to a wylde ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>berte / and become all vngodly and ſo be ſkarred fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of the goſpell. Therfore lybertye is not to be vſed afore them which haue not yet herd this maner of doctryne / as a fore / men not yet ſuffycyently confyrmed / but the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ample of ſaynt Poule is to be folowed: I haue ben weke to them that are weke:<note place="margin">i. Corin. viii.</note> If my meate doth offende my brother / I wyl ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer eate fleſſhe / leſt I offende my brother. But now where as the goſpell is clerely prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched / and the church meanely confirmed in the ſame / the gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uous obſeruacyon of vnprofy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb facs="tcp:6539:5"/>tradicyons is not gretly to be requyred. yea / Poul for to ſhew example of lyberte / he wolde not ſyrcumcyſe Tyte.<note place="margin">Gala. ii.</note> And Chriſt excuſed his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles / brekyng the tradicyons of the fathers / and ſayth:<note place="margin">Mathei. xxb.</note> Let them alone / they be blynd / and gydes of the blynde. &amp;ce.<note place="margin">Mat. xb xx .iii.</note> But yet in this thyng it is good to vſe ſobreneſſe and dyſcrecyon / for euen amonge enemyes ther be ſome that rather ſhulde be reconſyled than ſtyred &amp; prouo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked / and it beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth chriſten men to refarre all their doingꝭ not to their owne affectyons &amp; luſtes / but vnto the profyte of other / &amp; to the glory of Chriſt.<note place="margin">Apoc. v.</note> But many there be that breke auncyent cuſtomes / not to pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyte or do ſeruyce to other / or
<pb facs="tcp:6539:6"/>to do better thynges / but by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this lyberte delyteth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This is a wycked thynge to dyſpyce auncyent cuſtomes &amp; lawes / it is no chriſtyan thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge Furthermore / the brekynge of comen cuſtomes / redily ſtores vp gret vprore / and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mocio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ought not raſſhely to be excy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: for it is an harde thynge afterward to haue conſcyence that thou haſt gyuen occaſyon of comen calamytes &amp; myſeres</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d rule</note>The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d rule. Alſo in chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ryghtly inſtructe / there is to be had a conſyderacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſclaundre / leſt our example do hurte other / as theſe be: Ofte tymes not to force of the comen cuſtomes / &amp; to ſhew any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempte / &amp; to cauſe other to be forceles / or to gyue occaſyon
<pb facs="tcp:6539:6"/>to dyſſencyons / ſyſmes / ſectes or factions without neceſſary cauſe. If any man after this maner breketh tradicyons / cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taynly he doth ſynne. Without ſuche occaſyon of ſclaundres / we vndreſtande tradicyons to be free. This moderacyon &amp; equytye in tradicyons is very good to hold / for it kepeth the auctoryte of tradicyons &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth the comen cuſtomes &amp; good ordre / and it delyuereth mens conſcyences fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that old tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny / whan that they knowe that tradicyons be outwarde thynges &amp; indyfferent / &amp; maye be omytted &amp; lefte without ſyn except it be in caſe of ſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sclaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre of do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctryne.</note>Furthermore / the ſclaundres and offences of doctrynes / be moche worſe than euyll exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb facs="tcp:6539:7"/>i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maners. Therfore with great dilygence / a man muſt be ware / fyrſt that he teche no vngodly thynges / vncertayne or vnprofytable. Furthermore whan ye teache true thynges / that ye ſet theym not forthe ſo confuſely and doutefully / that the herers conceyue any euyll opinyons in ſuche confuſed and doutfull doctryne: as we ſe howe moche it profyteth the people to be monyſſhed after what maner mens tradicyons may be reproued: and agayne for what purpoſe / and to what vſe tradicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ought to be kept and loued. Excepte theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges be aptly &amp; diſcretly expreſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed / they that be vnlerned con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue a contempte of al lawes and cuſtomes. Thus alſo in
<pb facs="tcp:6539:7"/>other artycles / excepte they be aptly &amp; clerely expreſſed / there ryſe opinyons very perylous.</p>
            <p>Whan that men be iuſtifyed by fayth / how deteſtable opy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyons doth there ryſe / excepte the herers be monyſſhed what thing is entreated of / and that the perſone is reconcyled by fayth / and after that / our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyence is neceſſary / &amp; in men reconcyled / is ryghtouſneſſe.<note place="margin">Rom. v.</note> Lyke wyſe of free wyll / that god is not the cauſe of euyll / and many other thynges / that deſeruynge is not taken from workes / bycauſe we can do no thynge that can deſerue out of god / but bycauſe the promyſe of god is our forgyuenes / that the remiſſyon of ſynne may be certayne.<note place="margin">Fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yll</note>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. ii.</note>
               <note place="margin">Actus. ii</note> More ouer in men recon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyled
<pb facs="tcp:6539:8"/>/ good workes be alſo me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rytoryous.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ot. x.</note> So in all places dilygence muſt be gyuen / that without ſofeſtry or craft / they be expreſſed aptly &amp; diſtynctly Therfore wolde Paule that a byſſhop ſhuld be apte to teche that he ſhuld teche aptely and diſtynctly.<note place="margin">Titua. i</note> And Chriſt wolde that a lerned man / inſtructe in the kyngdome of god / ſhulde belyke vnto a good father of houſhold / which in his techi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g can vſe diſcrecyon in vttryng both newe thynges and olde. For excepte prechers vſe this diſerecyon &amp; dilygence / many mens conſcyences be ſore tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled / and euyll opinyons ryſe in their myndes / whiche wyll hurte religyon and maners / and than ſpringe vprores and
<pb facs="tcp:6539:8"/>many other maters of ſclaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre and offence. Therfore let vs beware and do oure dily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence that our maners beuty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye the goſpell. Moreouer al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo / that the waye of prechyng and playneſſe of the ſame may conforte mennes conſcyences / ryd them of all doutes / and redreſſe their erroures.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London in the Olde bayly in ſaynt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchres paryſſhe / by me Rychard Lant.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
